<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-02-14T18:11:12-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Joey Lovato</title><subtitle>Joey Lovato&apos;s personal website for poiesis, praxis, and theoria</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Post-Graduation in Brazil</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/praxis/2023/01/17/Brazil.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post-Graduation in Brazil" /><published>2023-01-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-01-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/praxis/2023/01/17/Brazil</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/praxis/2023/01/17/Brazil.html"><![CDATA[<p>After graduating with my masters, my partner and I set out on a two-week adventure in Brazil. What do you imagine when you think of Brazil, specifically Rio de Janeiro? Do you think of stunning beaches? Rolling green mountains? Christ the Redeemer? Indeed, these are the things I thought of too. As you can imagine, Rio was so much more than these things</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="praxis" /><category term="South America" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After graduating with my masters, my partner and I set out on a two-week adventure in Brazil. What do you imagine when you think of Brazil, specifically Rio de Janeiro? Do you think of stunning beaches? Rolling green mountains? Christ the Redeemer? Indeed, these are the things I thought of too. As you can imagine, Rio was so much more than these things]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do you name your car? 🚘</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/theoria/2022/09/12/Do-you-name-your-car.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do you name your car? 🚘" /><published>2022-09-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/theoria/2022/09/12/Do-you-name-your-car</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/theoria/2022/09/12/Do-you-name-your-car.html"><![CDATA[<p>The fascinating psychology behind our need to find the human in everything non-human.</p>

<p>I was recently sitting with my roommate doing homework at the dining room table when, in a string of procrastinating conversations, an interesting question was posed. As these conversations go, I can’t quite remember how we arrived at the topic, yet the question stands on its own: “Do you name your car(s)?” I was intrigued by this question because in my history of driving, naming my car has never crossed my mind—I suppose I don’t necessitate a name for a car as I would for, say, a dog or cat. Yet, as I continued talking with my roommate, I realized that naming cars might be just as normal for some people as not naming them is for me. But exactly why do people name inanimate objects? A quick google search with this query gave me a simple answer: <em>anthropomorphism</em>. But what exactly is that? In this article I’ll unpack this fascinating psychological phenomena as researched by leading experts in the field and reveal just how prevalent anthropomorphism is in our daily lives, from naming cars to new-age Artificial Intelligence.</p>

<p>You may be more familiar with anthropomorphism than you think. In its Latin roots we find a simple definition: <em>anthro-</em> meaning human and -<em>morphism</em> meaning taking other forms. So, in essence, anthropomorphism is simply non-human things taking on human characteristics. Anyone who has taken the ACT or studied literature to any degree is familiar with <em>personification</em> in writing, a close relative to anthropomorphism.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Earth felt the wound; and Nature from her seat, Sighing, through all her works, gave signs of woe.”- <em>John Milton, Paradise Lost</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>In this excerpt from John Milton, a common user of personification, Earth and Nature take on states of human emotion in a poetic use of figurative language. But, Milton’s rhetorical personification is just a subset of the entire anthropomorphic spectrum, a construct only recently researched in depth by psychologists.</p>

<p>Indeed, as you might imagine, projecting our humanity onto non-human objects has everything to do with our psychology (…and, I bet philosophers might also have a thing or two to say about this topic as well, but for the purposes of clear analytical reporting, we’ll stick to the psychologists). Nicholas Epley, Adam Waytz, and John T. Cacioppo, all leading experts in anthropomorphism, have published much of the research now canon in the field. The bulk of anthropomorphism’s history in psychology has been the study of assigning human characteristics to animals and the accuracy thereof. However, in a string of ground-breaking studies, Epley et. al shifted the focus onto us, the humans, to get to the bottom of why we anthropomorphize in the first place. The answers are somewhat simple, but actually employ the work of many sub-fields of psychology, including social, cognitive, and development psychology and even neurosciences (Epley et. al 2010).</p>

<p>As defined by Epley et. al, anthropomorphism:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“involves going beyond behavioral descriptions of imagined or observed actions (e.g. <em>the dog is affectionate</em>) to represent an agent’s mental or physical characteristics using humanlike descriptors (e.g. <em>the dog loves me</em>)” - <em>Epley et. al 2007</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I included this quote because it clarifies an important point. The qualification of characteristics being “humanlike” is certainly dependent on your personal opinion and perspective. But, for the context of psychological research, these nuances aren’t as important. We’ll leave the intricacies of that topic to the philosophers. For us it is only necessary to understand that humans project many of their qualities and actions (such as the act of loving) onto non-human things.</p>

<p>The research of Epley et. al compartmentalizes this idea by posing the psychological variability in anthropomorphism: some things are anthropomorphized more than others; children seem to anthropomorphize more than adults and further some adults more than others; some contexts and cultures evoke more anthropomorphism than others. To explain these variabilities, the researchers proposed their three-factor theory of anthropomorphism, a simple yet versatile hypothesis that deepens our understanding of why we see the human in everything non-human. The three factors are, in order of their acronym: Sociality, Effectance, and Elicited agent Knowledge (SEEK) (Epley et. al 2007). Beyond these somewhat complex terms exist easy-to-grasp ideas with hosts of research proving their accuracy. In the coming sections I will briefly explore each of these determinants of anthropomorphism, after which I will provide some much-promised modern relevance.</p>

<p><strong>Sociality</strong></p>

<p>This first factor of anthropomorphism is a well-defined construct in society: <em>in lack of social connection, we fabricate it</em>. With no doubt, and thanks to leagues of social psychology research, we know that humans are extremely social creatures with respective social needs. So, as it appears to Epley et. al, those social needs are crucial in the process of anthropomorphism within our conscience. Consider someone who is very lonely:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“One method of regaining social connection, we have suggested, is to anthropomorphize non-human agents, essentially creating humans out of non-humans. People may be especially likely, then, to anthropomorphize non-human agents when they are feeling socially disconnected” -<em>Epley et. al 2007</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>To test this hypothesis, the researchers took a survey of college students, measuring the students’ degree of loneliness against their anthropomorphic tendencies towards their pets. The results of the survey showed the predicted correlation between social disconnection and anthropomorphism—the lonelier a subject was, the more likely they were to anthropomorphize their pets. But, the sociality of anthropomorphism already held strong cultural evidence before the academic stamp-of-approval. One famous example comes from the classic movie Cast Away. When stranded on an island, Tom Hanks constructs a friend from a Wilson volleyball. Hanks’ crippling depression upon losing his friend to ocean currents shows—albeit fictional—the authentic relationships people can build with non-human objects via anthropomorphism. I would be remiss to say I didn’t shed a tear myself watching Wilson float away.</p>

<figure align="center">
    <img width="40%" src="/assets/images/car/castaway.jpeg" />
    <figcaption>Wilson,_DreamWorks Pictures</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Younger readers might remember a similar anthropomorphic scene from SpongeBob SquarePants. When SpongeBob secludes himself to his pineapple in fear of the outside world, he befriends a penny, chip, and used napkin, giving each a personality—sociality anthropomorphism at its finest (not to mention that SpongeBob himself is an anthropomorphized sponge, but I won’t get too “meta”).</p>

<figure align="center">
    <img width="40%" src="/assets/images/car/spongebob.png" />
    <figcaption>SpongeBob's inanimate friends, Nickelodeon</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>Effectance</strong></p>

<p>This next factor of anthropomorphism, while a bit more convoluted than sociality, is equally as important. The term <em>effectance</em> in psychology is usually paired with motivation:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Effectance motivation entails the desire to reduce uncertainty and ambiguity, at least in part with the goal of attaining a sense of predictability in the environment.” -<em>Epley et. al 2007</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>We live in a chaotic world—this is no doubt—and thus we find ways to make sense of it all. The researchers go on to argue that anthropomorphism is one of those ways. Our deep understanding of “how to be human” spills over into our interactions with our surroundings, prompting our inner psyche to treat non-human things as humans in order to better understand them. Also, a facet of this effectance anthropomorphism is control, meaning that by projecting human characteristics onto non-humans, we can better control those things. In another survey, the researchers proved this by asking participants to watch videos of two dogs, one showing unpredictable behavior and another predictable behavior. Upon measuring the participants’ “desire for control” against their anthropomorphic rating of the two dogs, those participants with a higher desire for control showed higher anthropomorphic ratings of the unpredictable dog. The results of this study confirm that when we are confused about something in our environment, we tend to apply our honed human-to-human analytical skills to the situation.</p>

<p>But, once again, we didn’t necessarily need an academic study to prove what has been culturally obvious for millennia.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The tendency to see humanlike figurers among the constellations, humanlike religious agents guiding weather patterns, or humanlike ghosts and spirits causing madness and psychological dysfunction has long been explained as a logical attempt by humans to understand and predict the complicated world around them using existing knowledge about human agents.” -<em>Epley et. al 2007</em></p>
</blockquote>

<figure align="center">
    <img width="40%" src="/assets/images/car/const.png" />
    <figcaption>Constellations, stellarium-web.org</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Since our beginnings we have sought to understand the mysteries of our cosmic existence via our human intuitions. Another modern example of effectance anthropomorphism is COVID-19. Much of the language used to explain the virus attributes human actions, such as “waging war against COVID” or “the virus has come back with a vengeance.” COVID-19, a non-living jumble of organic material has cost the lives of millions of people—humanizing the virus is our way to cope and attempt to control its threat to humanity.</p>

<figure align="center">
    <img width="40%" src="/assets/images/car/covid.jpg" />
    <figcaption>COVID school bully, John Dark, Columbia Missourian</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>Elicited Agent Knowledge</strong></p>

<p>The last factor of the researchers’ theory is rooted in cognitive science, where the principles of our cognition serve to enhance the likelihood of anthropomorphism. Within the basic human cognitive model, we intake knowledge through our sense, process that information by activating previously stored knowledge, then act on that knowledge. Epley et. al propose that when interacting with non-human objects, humans use their stored knowledge of humans for three primary reasons. First, because we are inherently human and bound by our human bodies, we lack the knowledge of non-human objects through any other perspective but our own. Despite some convincing costumes at Halloween parties, we only really know how to be human.</p>

<p>Second, humans have “mirror” neurons which are activated when attempting to mimic actions perceived by things in the environment. Because we mirror our surroundings using human actions, we tend to perceive our surroundings as taking on human qualities. These “mirror” neurons are crucial to our emphatic faculties (feeling what other people are feeling), but it turns out that they do the same for non-humans.</p>

<p>Lastly, babies’ entire worlds revolve around interactions with other humans. It is not until later in their cognitive development that children begin to recognize the difference between what is human and non-human. Yet, it seems that the residual effects of our anthropocentric childhoods ripple into our adult lives. Certainly adults understand that dogs aren’t human, yet that doesn’t stop the tickling of our subconscious telling us to treat them like humans (Epley et. al 2007).</p>

<p>In short, our brains are wired to understand humans, and that’s what they do, even if what they’re perceiving isn’t always human. (The same reason why putting brownie mix into a cupcake tin will produce cupcake shaped brownies. The content of the dessert is still brownie, but they take on a cupcake shape).</p>

<p><strong>Modern Relevance</strong></p>

<p>So, do you have a better understanding of why you might name your car? If the technicalities of the three-factor theory of anthropomorphism went over your head, here’s the TL;DR: one might name their car because (a) they are lonely and desire human connection, (b) they are attempting to understand or control the car when faced with unpredictable behavior, or (c) they simply can’t help but see the car as human because of innate anthropomorphic circuitry in their brain.</p>

<p>However, anthropomorphism has much broader (and more serious) relevance than the naming of cars. Our trusted researchers, in a 2010 follow-up paper to their initial theory of anthropomorphism, laid out many topics outside of psychology where anthropomorphism applies.</p>

<p>One of the most prominent topics is human-computer interaction. It is clear that in today’s society, computers and smart-phones consume our attention, despite a constant debate on technology’s trustworthiness. What makes an app seem trustworthy? What makes a voice assistant more easily accessible? How should a self-driving car react to moral dilemmas on the road? All of these questions, and more, are derived from anthropomorphism: What makes a person more trustworthy? What makes a person easier to talk to? How might a human react to moral dilemmas on the road?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Computer scientists, robotics developers, and engineers can use anthropomorphism research in their efforts to optimize technology by focusing on the consequences of anthropomorphism and also identifying the people that are most prone to these consequences” -<em>Epley et al. 2010</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>What the researchers are getting at here applies to other topics as well. People are susceptible to anthropomorphism, and that can be taken advantage of. Why do cars still have headlights that look like eyes and a grill that looks like a smile? Why is the Progressive Insurance mascot an insurance package with eyes and a mouth? Market researchers know a thing or two about anthropomorphism… just look around and you’ll begin to see your reflection in many things you buy.</p>

<p>And finally, back to our friend John Milton. How does humanizing the earth or nature affect how we treat them? Environmental science might just incorporate a thing or two from anthropomorphism as well.</p>

<p>I hope you can take this knowledge of anthropomorphism with you for the next few days and make note of all of your anthropomorphic tendencies. But don’t think you need to stop by any means. After all, you are <em>only</em> human.</p>

<p><strong>References</strong></p>

<p>Epley, N., Waytz, A., &amp; Cacioppo, J. T. (2007). On seeing human: A three-factor theory of anthropomorphism. <em>Psychological Review</em>, <em>114</em>(4), 864–886. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-295x.114.4.864">https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-295x.114.4.864</a></p>

<p>Epley, N., Waytz, A., Akalis, S., &amp; Cacioppo, J. T. (2008). When we need a human: Motivational determinants of anthropomorphism. <em>Social Cognition, 26</em>(2), 143–155. <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doi/10.1521/soco.2008.26.2.143">https://doi.org/10.1521/soco.2008.26.2.143</a></p>

<p>Epley, N., Waytz, A., &amp; Cacioppo, J. T. (2010). Who Sees Human?: The Stability and Importance of Individual Differences in Anthropomorphism. <em>Perspectives on Psychological Science</em>, <em>5</em>(3), 219–232. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1745691610369336">https://doi.org/10.1177/1745691610369336</a></p>

<p><em>Adapted from an assignment I did in a psychology course</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="theoria" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The fascinating psychology behind our need to find the human in everything non-human.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First NSA Conference</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/praxis/2022/06/30/NSA-Conference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First NSA Conference" /><published>2022-06-30T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-06-30T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/praxis/2022/06/30/NSA-Conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/praxis/2022/06/30/NSA-Conference.html"><![CDATA[<p>My stutter is a gift. That’s right, the thing that adds extra s-s-syllables to my speech and makes words a little harder to say… its a gift. Why? Because it has challenged me; it has led me to the most amazing people; it has opened my eyes to a brave and supportive community; and it has fundamentally changed how I answer the question: <em>what is a voice?</em> My voice is my stutter, and my stutter is my voice.</p>

<p><img align="right" width="40%" style="padding-left:10pt" src="/assets/images/nsa/vea.jpg" /></p>

<p>Around a year and half ago, I was on my computer doing homework when a thought popped into my head. <em>There must be a conference for people who stutter! There must be.</em> A few google searches later and I landed on the National Stuttering Association website (<a href="westutter.com">westutter.com</a>). The countdown for the next conference was only a few months away, so I knew it was too late to go. So I waited, then revisited the page this spring and registered for the 2022 NSA Conference in Newport Beach, California! Thanks to the generosity of my <a href="https://harveyscholars.mines.edu/vision/">scholarship donors</a>, I was able to get all of the conference expenses paid for!</p>

<p>The months leading up to the conference, I wasn’t nervous at all. I’m pretty comfortable with my stutter and I have worked hard to accept it into my life. That excitement continued as I boarded my Tuesday evening flight from Denver to Orange County. And then I landed, and a tickle of nervousness crept into my belly. And then I got to the hotel late on the eve of the first day of the conference and I heard a stutter that wasn’t my own! Someone in the lobby was talking to the hotel concierge and stuttering! The nerves set in even deeper.</p>

<p><img align="left" width="40%" style="padding-right:10pt" src="/assets/images/nsa/nametag.jpg" /></p>

<p>The next morning I meandered to the lobby as the check-in time of 12pm neared. I knew absolutely <strong>zero</strong> people. To be honest, I was terrified. I waited in line to register, hearing stutters echo around me and I felt like running away and hiding. I managed to have a few conversations, but I was still feeling awful. I escaped the crowded lobby and headed back to my room, an instinct that fellow introverts can surely relate to. On my way to my room, a man was seated on a bench in the hallway. He was a bit older, but his name badge was very long and colorful, indicating a long tenure with the NSA. We made eye contact and I slowed down. He got out of his chair and asked me my name and whether I was a Person Who Stutters (PWS). I responded yes. I think he could see my nervousness, so he said, “Go out there and be in as many conversations as you can, meet as many people as you can”. In that moment, that advice seemed impossible. I wanted to do quite the opposite. But, his voice had a ring of truth, so I held onto his advice as I thanked him and returned to my room. I called my mom and my boyfriend to ground myself before taking a deep breath and going back down to the lobby for the first event: a first-timers workshop. Within the course of an hour, my entire perspective changed. I was no longer in the “real-world”. I was with my people. I was with other stutters who understood not only what it feels like to have a stutter, but what it feels like to be alone. <em>I surely wasn’t alone anymore.</em></p>

<p><img align="right" width="40%" style="padding-left:10pt" src="/assets/images/nsa/beach.png" /></p>

<p>The next few days proved to be life-changing in all the ways I had predicted and all of the ways I hadn’t. I met stutters younger than me. Stutters my age. Stutters older than me. Stutters from all over the country and world. Stutters with small s-stutters. Stutters with l-l-l-l-l-l-l-l-l-l-l-l-l-l-l-long s-s-s-s-s-stutters. Stutters who are overt (they stutter in front of anyone and everyone). Stutters who are covert (they sometimes hide their stutter using tricks like changing words. I found out that I am a pretty covert stutterer). I also met many supporters of stutters, including but not limited to: fathers, mothers, brothers, sisters, spouses, speech language pathologists, and friends. I went to many workshops, including one on stuttering acceptance, a covert open-mic (which I was able to speak at and tell my story), and a “Passing Twice” workshop. This was a workshop for people who stutter and are in the LGBTQ+ community. In the workshop I heard the most amazing stories from people who have risen up to accept themselves in their stutter and sexuality/gender identity. After the workshop, they offered a sign-up link for anyone who wanted to continue the conversation at a dinner the following evening. At this point in the conference, I was leaning heavily on the advice of the man in the hallway, so I said <em>why not!</em> and I signed up.</p>

<p><img align="left" width="40%" style="padding-right:10pt" src="/assets/images/nsa/group.png" /></p>

<p>When I showed up in the lobby to walk to dinner with the others who had signed-up, I had no clue that many of them would become dear friends of mine. Over the course of the next few days I came to know and respect a group of amazing human beings, all with an inspiring story (or two). We talked and talked and talked and talked, and stuttered and stuttered and stuttered and it felt <em>SO GOOD</em>. We were all truly in heaven, and consistently reminding each other that the NSA conference was something really special. Many long-time NSA Conference attendees told me over and over again that the conference was an inflection point for them, especially when I introduced myself as a first-timer. I heard excitement in their voice as they realized I was experiencing the conference for the very first time, possibly as they reminisced memories of their first conference, years or decades before.</p>

<p>I stuttered more in the span of 4 days than I have in last 4 months, and it felt amazing. Being there among fellow stutterers truly changed how I view stuttering. For much of my life, I viewed my stutter as a burden to those around me– something to hide and mask. But, hearing so many beautiful stutters taught me the power of patience and graciousness in a world that expects us to speak too quickly. The conversations I had were deep, engaging, and heartfelt. The stutters were open and free to dance in their repetitions and blocks (a block is when a stutter is silent, making it seem like the stutterer has paused).</p>

<p><img align="right" width="30%" style="padding-left:10pt" src="/assets/images/nsa/dance.png" /></p>

<p>At the final Saturday night banquet, by happenstance, I sat next to the man that I met in the hallway on the very first day. I told him that his advice was brilliant, and that my conference had been particularly magical because of it. The rest of the night, my new friends and I danced and celebrated together, holding each moment close to our hearts as we prepared to depart back to the “real-world”. I intend on attending many more NSA conferences over the coming years, but I this one will remain close to my heart as it was my first conference. My first time meeting that many stutterers. My first time learning true patience. My first time understanding the support provided by the NSA. And my first time <em>truly</em> letting my stutter fly :)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="praxis" /><category term="stuttering" /><category term="conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My stutter is a gift. That’s right, the thing that adds extra s-s-syllables to my speech and makes words a little harder to say… its a gift. Why? Because it has challenged me; it has led me to the most amazing people; it has opened my eyes to a brave and supportive community; and it has fundamentally changed how I answer the question: what is a voice? My voice is my stutter, and my stutter is my voice.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/misc/2022/05/30/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2022-05-30T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-05-30T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/misc/2022/05/30/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/misc/2022/05/30/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ll find this post in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll serve</code>, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</p>

<p>Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP</code></p>

<p>Where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR</code> is a four-digit number, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MONTH</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">DAY</code> are both two-digit numbers, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MARKUP</code> is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.</p>

<p>Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Hi, </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
<span class="n">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'Tom'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="c1">#=&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home">Jekyll docs</a> for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll’s GitHub repo</a>. If you have questions, you can ask them on <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll Talk</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="tutorial" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Post</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/06/first-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Post" /><published>2022-05-06T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-05-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/06/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/06/first-post.html"><![CDATA[<p>lalal</p>

<h1 id="test">TEST</h1>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tutorial" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[lalal]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Study Abroad Part Two</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/praxis/2020/02/19/Rome-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Study Abroad Part Two" /><published>2020-02-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-02-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/praxis/2020/02/19/Rome-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/praxis/2020/02/19/Rome-2.html"><![CDATA[<p>Chaos Theory; Groceries; Oh Won’t You</p>

<p>Welcome back my faithful virtual friends. In this post, I explore a few things mathematical, a few things dogmatical, a few things emblematical, and a few things fanatical… Because!… I am on sabbatical. Ohhh, isn’t rhyming fun? Well, so is being abroad. Enjoy my microcosm of Rome, presented to you via the one and only world wide web.</p>

<h3 id="-chaos-theory">🌀 Chaos Theory</h3>
<p>Walking the streets of Rome are an activity beyond transportation. To get from my apartment to class, I must tiptoe through Trastevere. From the Roman Forum to lunch; stroll along the Tiber. From H&amp;M to the park; strut along pedestrian boulevards —and this is what I am coming to love about this city. You don’t get in a car and zone out for 20 minutes. Instead, you’re forced to interact with the city, smelling food, hearing conversations, and rummaging through streets filled with people of all varieties, leading storied lives.</p>

<p>Okay, so there’s a lot to unpack in the preceding paragraph. But for this week, I want to take a moment to explore a consequence of that last point. As you walk through any city, it is clear that much of the respective complexity comes from the large quantity of people, each pursuing their individual daily actions. Martha goes to get her nails done. Tony goes to school. Cassandra goes to work at the cafe. Luke goes to dinner. And on and on and on. But, in Rome, specifically Trastevere, this complexity can be seen on a more human level than most American cities, where cars dominate the transportation system. For example, there is an intersection in Trastevere which I walk through multiple times a day. It connects one large road and 3 smaller ones, all of which are cobblestone. A café and restaurant occupy the corners, the café being an extremely busy establishment. Each time I walk through this intersection, I am impressed by the quantity of people (and some vehicles) which pass through every minute, seen below.</p>

<center><img width="60%" style="padding-left:10pt" src="/assets/images/rome-2/Trastevere-Intersection.jpg" />
<br />Intersection of Via di Porta Settimiana, Via di Santa Dorotea, Via Garibaldi and Via della Scala (looking south)\
</center>

<p>As I sit at the busy café with my coffee, I see students, newspaper distributers, couples, groups of friends, school children, elderly women and many others, coming from one way and going another. It all seems very chaotic. Every bump, honk and conversation affecting the next minute of activity. This notion of chaos, one of the reason’s I chose to study road-systems for my practicum, is inherently difficult to model. There are so many variables and human decisions in that one intersection, it becomes difficult to imagine blowing the scale up to the entirety of Rome.</p>

<p>Edward Lorenz, a mathematician and meteorologist who worked primarily in the 20th century, was a pioneer in modeling chaos, something which had been an oxymoron for much of the study of mathematics before his time. Through his research with atmospheric modeling equations, he concluded that some systems are very sensitive to initial conditions, such that even a 0.001% change in starting values will completely alter the resulting trajectory of the system. A common example of this is the double-rod pendulum, whose motion is extremely chaotic despite the simplicity of the mechanisms in place. Lorenz also showed that despite chaos, groups of initial conditions can be attracted to central locations, thus birthing his famous Lorenz Attractor graphs, seen below.</p>

<center><img width="40%" style="padding-left:10pt" src="/assets/images/rome-2/Lorenz_attractor_yb.png" />
</center>

<p>Lorenz’s Strange Attractor: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butterfly_effect#/media/File:Lorenz_attractor_yb.svg">Source</a></p>

<p>Researching chaos theory has opened my eyes to just how we might be able to model road systems. Rome’s road systems are chaotic, but I feel there is an underlying mechanism at play. What the mechanism is, I’m still unsure, but with Lorenz’s ideas in my tool belt, I am initiating a few experimental procedures to further my research:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>I have set up a GPS logger on my phone. This raw data will be useful to my analyses of using Rome’s road system over long periods of time (3 months)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The intersection in Trastevere I spoke of earlier, drawn below, will become my primary data-gathering center during the next few weeks. I really want to investigate what is going one here, and I predict that analyzing one intersection in Rome (which is within my grasp) might reveal hints to the function of the entire city.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<center><img width="40%" style="padding-left:10pt" src="/assets/images/rome-2/North-Trastevere.jpg" />
</center>

<p>The intersection is in blue</p>

<h3 id="weekly-anecdote--groceries">Weekly Anecdote: 🛒 Groceries</h3>
<p>In a place which is unfamiliar, I find that habitual tendencies help to make it more familiar over time. Thus, I’m not surprised that over the last month, I have formed a habit of making pilgrimage to the grocery store every Monday morning. I don’t have class in the morning, so I can take my time getting up, eating breakfast, and making the journey. But, would I make this the weekly anecdote if there wasn’t a but? Well, here it is… But, last Wednesday was a bit different. I got a late start to the day, so I only had ~1 hour to make the trip before class. After fast-walking there and doing my typical path through the produce, bakery and various isles, I paid and double stepped the stairs back up to the sidewalk (the store is in the basement of a clothing retailer). So there I was with three heavy bags filled with much more that I had intended on getting (a common problem of mine) and only ~20 minutes to make it all the way home and then to class. I knew that with the load, I was not going to be able to walk. But, propped gracefully on their kickstands near the edge of the sidewalk were two red bikes. They were JUMP bikes. I had seen them many times before and vaguely knew that they were rental bikes made by Uber. Luckily, I had downloaded the app knowing that I would, at some point, try one. So, I scanned the QR code on the bike, fumbled with the lock until it came undone, put one bag in the basket and one on either handle, saddled up and put the kickstand in its horizontal position. The next part of this story still makes me chuckle. These JUMP bikes turn out to be partly motorized! So, one turn of the pedal shot me down the sidewalk. Ahhhh! Imagine me, an American guy on a red bike, speeding down the streets of Rome with groceries bags knocking into his knees, swerving around curbs and bumpy cobblestone. I did end up making it home and to class on time… phew.</p>

<p>So, what did I learn from this little adventure? First, riding a bike in Rome is an acquired talent (quite unlike anything I’ve experienced before—it’s more like playing dodgeball than riding a bike). Second, it is usually strenuous circumstances which make us try the craziest things. Third, although scary the first time, Rome’s roads are quite accommodating to multiple means of transportation. And finally, I learned when I do this again, to make sure the eggs are at the top of the bag. Last week Rome’s roads ripped my pants. This week, they cracked a half-dozen eggs—through vibration, yes—but still. Curses.</p>

<p>More on those JUMP bikes next week. I’m intrigued :)</p>

<h3 id="️-oh-wont-you">❤️ Oh Won’t You</h3>
<p>Oh, Roma…
Won’t you sing to me in the moonlight
Won’t you call out my name
Won’t you mingle in the night
Won’t you know your fame</p>

<p>Won’t you share your legions of aroma
Won’t you spritz perfume
Won’t you take me home-a
Won’t you arise from a tomb</p>

<p>Won’t you open of bottle of wine
Won’t you fall in love
Won’t you build a shrine
Won’t you tell me what you’re made of</p>

<p>Won’t you feel the buzz
Won’t you give me roses
Won’t you do what Santa Maria does
Won’t you be what prose is</p>

<p>Oh Roma…
Won’t you be my cloud nine
Won’t you consider it, please
Won’t you be my Valentine
Because I’m in love, won’t you see</p>

<h3 id="-until-next-time">👋 Until Next Time</h3>
<p>Thank you, again, for reading my blog. As I investigate, uncover, and research the essence of this city, I’m finding that Rome has just as much to say about itself as it does about me. Assimilation is more than osmosis… it’s a becoming. Until next time… Ciao!</p>

<h3 id="well-there-was-no-next-time">Well… there was no next time</h3>
<p>Unfortunately, in the weeks after I wrote this blog, COVID-19 swept through Italy, and then the world. I had to come home early from my study abroad 😢 But, the time I did have in Europe was *chefs kiss*. In the two weeks prior to flying back to the US, I was able to travel to the UK, exploring London, Edinburgh, and Glasgow. COVID-19 was a shock to all of us—and many people suffered much <em>much</em> more than me. So, I’m not bitter. But, I do have an intense motivation to get back out there and make up the 2 months that I lost… and many more 😄</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="praxis" /><category term="Study Abroad" /><category term="Europe" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Chaos Theory; Groceries; Oh Won’t You]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Study Abroad Part One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/praxis/2020/02/02/Rome-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Study Abroad Part One" /><published>2020-02-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-02-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/praxis/2020/02/02/Rome-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/praxis/2020/02/02/Rome-1.html"><![CDATA[<p>Arriving; Sedimentary; Campaign Bridges; Cobblestone Voices; Rome Ripped my Jeans</p>

<p>Welcome to my first Study Abroad Blog Post! I will be investigating the role of road systems in cities while exploring Rome, as a part of a semester-long project through the McBride Honors Program at the Colorado School of Mines. This experience, among many personal, spiritual, and academic motivations, is an opportunity to practice many of the interpersonal, analytical, and research skills I have been learning at Mines (hence the name: Practicum). Adapt, share, experience, investigate, assimilate… just a few of the verbs I would use to describe this trip. FYI, before traveling to Rome, I wrote a research paper on road systems, which can be found <a href="/downloads/Research-Paper-Practicum-Joey_Lovato.pdf">here</a>. Now on with the post!</p>

<h3 id="️-arriving">✈️ Arriving</h3>
<p>9am. In the fog of jetlag and a Mediterranean sea breeze, I made my way from the Fiumicino Airport to Rome’s quaint Trastevere neighborhood. On the way, I took note of the narrow, elevated highways of the outer city. Cars, buses and trucks alike drove with incredible speed, changing lanes, merging and honking with no fear of crashing or hurting each other’s feelings. Aggressive driving was seemingly the norm (something I have already gotten very used to while living here). After a few tight turns, some of which I thought to be impossible, and a few bridge crossings later, we arrived at the apartments. When I stepped off the bus, only in the bowels of my head-ached mind did I fully realize I was in the middle of the Eternal City. An instinctive mission took over my body, and with the little energy I had left, I found my room and took to a sobering dreamless sleep.</p>

<h3 id="-sedimentary">🍰 Sedimentary</h3>
<p>I can feel, hear, see, touch and smell the history in Rome, deeply layered in the fabric of the city. As I walk from my apartment to class, from class to dinner, and from dinner to the river, it is clear that I am using roads traversed by thousands, if not millions before me, for thousands of years. A city this old has a few obvious and subtle hints to its age. Of course, as I walk under an arch from the 3rd century CE, it is clear that physical monuments reveal a city strewn through time, the tufa and marble of an infrastructure once at the center of a Mediterranean Republic embedded in the hills. The Colosseum, Roman Forum, Pantheon and other famous sights in Rome, all of which I visited in this first week, are quite large reminders of this ancient presence. But, it is in a deeper analysis of the city… and I mean deeper literally, that more subtle things emerge. When I first walked along the Tiber River, I made note of steep walls which extend from the stone river banks to the city “ground-zero.” It was after a discussion in my first on-site class (titled Ancient Rome and its Monuments, taught by Professor Hansen, a seriously amazing historian and teacher who finds ancient monuments “sexy”) that I realized the entire city is built upon older versions of itself. Many of the ancient monuments in Rome are nearer to the level of the river, hidden in pits around the city, viewable by railing from the sidewalk. Might I say… Rome is sedimentary.</p>

<h3 id="-campaign-bridges">📜 Campaign Bridges</h3>
<p>It was also during my first on-site class that we discussed bridges, and their importance to Rome’s ancient road system. During the early years of ancient Rome, the city was responsible for much of the commerce from northern Italy to the Mediterranean via the Tiber River. Thus, crossing the river had great economic value, leading to the strategic construction of bridges. Yes, “All Roads Lead to Rome”, but this is also partially true before it was the center of the Roman Empire. One such bridge, built by Lucio Fabricio around 62-23 BC, is one of two bridges to connect Tiber Island to the mainland, pictured below.</p>

<center><img width="60%" style="padding-left:10pt" src="/assets/images/rome-1/Ponte_Fabricio_Rome_Pierleoni.jpg" /></center>

<p>Engraved at the crest of the two large arches on both sides reads the family name of Lucio Fabricio. At first glance, this name seems simple… structures bearing the name of their constructor is common. But, given the context of Rome when this bridge was built, we gain a fuller understanding of the engraving. At this point in time, senators, who were voted for by their state, would gather in the Roman Forum to discuss politics. But in a time lacking social media, T.V., or even a printing press, the popularity of candidates for senator was primarily word of mouth. Thus, by inscribing your name on a bridge in ancient Rome, you’re essentially saying, “Hey, look at this bridge… yep, I built it. Impressive right? Ya, that’s the kind of stuff I do.” Bridges were campaign ads. And by using his family name, Lucio could guarantee that his predecessors would reap the rewards of credibility for centuries.</p>

<p>So, yes… the role of role systems in cities include transportation, identity and adaptation (callback to my essay). But, from this story of campaign bridges in ancient Rome, it seems that road systems have the ability to provide freedom of expression to a city’s people. Cities are primarily planned by governments, but much of the infrastructure is built by the citizens themselves. Whether it be a bridge in ancient Rome or highway in modern America, these infrastructure projects are pieces of art designed by the people and for the people.</p>

<h3 id="-cobblestone-voices">🇮🇹 Cobblestone Voices</h3>
<p>I cannot finish my first post without mentioning, of course, cobblestone. Covering many of the pedestrian and characteristic streets in Rome, I have grown particularly fond of its ability to transport me back in time. While walking around Trastevere, the neighborhood of my apartments and university, if I orient myself just right and erase the electric lights from my perception, I could very well be in 1670.</p>

<p>Something of interest to me, which sprung naturally from looking down at the cobblestone every day, is the pattern of such streets. Sampietrini, the name of Rome’s classic black basalt cobblestone roads, are found in two patterns: a classic grid and a recursive arch design, drawn below.</p>

<center><img width="60%" style="padding-left:10pt" src="/assets/images/rome-1/cobblestone.jpg" /></center>

<p>Both hypnotic in their repetitive natures, the cobblestone streets have proven to me, in new and fascinating ways, the importance of rode systems to a city. The cobblestone screams identity: <em>Io sono Italiano!</em> Translation: <em>I am Italian!</em> The city is always communicating to me: a whisper in the fog of the tiber; an accusation in the honk of a motorbike; a song in the bells of a church; And through the mossy irrigation of Rome’s cobblestone streets comes a lusty voice of cultural roots, sunken deep into the soil of a city whose pride is known worldwide. <em>Io sono Italiano! Io sono Italiano! Io sono Italiano!</em></p>

<h3 id="weekly-anecdote-️-rome-ripped-my-jeans">Weekly Anecdote: 🛤️ Rome Ripped my Jeans</h3>
<p>This week’s story begins one late evening on the fringes of Trastevere. Let me set this up… it was quite cold on this particular night, so not only were my friends and I on a rush to get home, but my arms were also tucked <em>pretty</em> close to my side. So, when the pedestrian walk-sign illuminated a little green man, I decided to shuffle-run across the road. But, what I hadn’t accounted for were the large rails embedded in the road… the tram line. So, naturally, the brown soles of my Vans caught on this perfect tripping device, and…. Let’s just say this: As I write this, I sit here looking at a large scar on my lower palm and a similar one on my knee. I left a bit of myself on that road. But, that’s just a part of the job when you’re doing a research paper on road systems; how more intimate can you get? Ripped jeans is a small price for true first-hand research.</p>

<p>👋 Until Next Time
And we made it! Thank you for reading my first Study Abroad blog post. Living in Rome is becoming exponentially more exciting, novel and mysterious every day. So if you thought this post was gripping, just wait… until next time. Ciao!</p>

<center><img width="30%" style="padding-left:10pt" src="/assets/images/rome-1/cat.jpg" /></center>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="praxis" /><category term="Study Abroad" /><category term="Europe" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Arriving; Sedimentary; Campaign Bridges; Cobblestone Voices; Rome Ripped my Jeans]]></summary></entry></feed>